<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Sean Kearney 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-do&#34;&gt;What I do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after graduating with my PhD from MIT, I took off to Tokyo, Japan thanks to a fellowship from the Japanese Society for the Promotion of Science. I am now working in the lab of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microbiolimmunol.med.keio.ac.jp/home.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kenya Honda&lt;/a&gt; on a couple of projects to discern the molecular bases for protective effects of bacteria on their hosts. Now, and during my PhD, I focus on a few main questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do bacteria move through the environment, and what are the environmental cues that allow microorganisms to distinguish hospitable from inhospitable environments?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What environmental features ensure the growth, maintenance, and persistent colonization of microorganisms introduced into new ecosystems? That is, what constraints should we consider when constructing a microbial niche?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the consequences of microbial physiological activities on their environments and how do these feedback into microbial physiology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-care-about&#34;&gt;What I care about&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals have always been an important part of my life, and I have a lot of compassion and empathy for them. I spend a lot of time thinking about animal welfare and more broadly welfare and equitability for the disenfranchised. On this front, I volunteer with animal rights organizations and look for ways to encourage people to adopt more compassionate diets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Science</title>
      <link>/about/science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/science/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;microbial-ecology&#34;&gt;Microbial Ecology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking on the scale of microorganisms can be really challenging as a macroorganism. While the intuition and approaches developed for macroecology may have relevance in microbial ecosytems, in many ways, I think it is misleading to think about microbial ecology as a miniature version of macrobial ecology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate education in bioprocess engineering emphasizes scaling up bench-scale technologies to industrial scale fermentations. Unfortunately, scale-up is a nontrivial process, particularly for cell culture, as behaviors and physiology of cells at the lab scale often completely change in &amp;gt;1000 L reactors. In a similar way, the behavior of microorganisms on small scales, even when in isolation, is not as predictable as simply scaling down observations from bulk culture growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to do a PhD in biological engineering because I wanted to develop new tools to study microorganisms and microbial ecology that do not rely on extrapolation of intuitions from macroscale biological processes. In order to do so, I think it is important to abandon assumptions about how things are going to work, and in a sense, meet the microbes where they&amp;rsquo;re at. To me, this mentality requires new approaches: ways of identifying microbial populations, predicting how microorganisms respond to perturbations, and how isogenic microbial populations differentiate in time and space in response to microscale changes in their environments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/contact/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contact/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Endospores and other lysis-resistant bacteria comprise a widely shared core community within the human microbiota</title>
      <link>/content/publication/kearney-endospores-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/kearney-endospores-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal dietary niche enables reversible engraftment of a gut bacterial commensal</title>
      <link>/content/publication/kearney-orthogonal-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/kearney-orthogonal-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictability and persistence of prebiotic dietary supplementation in a healthy human cohort</title>
      <link>/content/publication/gurry-predictability-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/gurry-predictability-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salt-responsive gut commensal modulates T H 17 axis and disease</title>
      <link>/content/publication/wilck-salt-responsive-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/wilck-salt-responsive-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two dynamic regimes in the human gut microbiome</title>
      <link>/content/publication/gibbons-two-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/gibbons-two-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recurrent Clostridium difficile infection associates with distinct bile acid and microbiome profiles</title>
      <link>/content/publication/allegretti-recurrent-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/allegretti-recurrent-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dietary microbes modulate transgenerational cancer risk</title>
      <link>/content/publication/poutahidis-dietary-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/poutahidis-dietary-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maternal gut microbes control offspring sex and survival</title>
      <link>/content/publication/ibrahim-maternal-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/ibrahim-maternal-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whole genome comparison of a large collection of mycobacteriophages reveals a continuum of phage genetic diversity</title>
      <link>/content/publication/pope-whole-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/pope-whole-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbial reprogramming inhibits Western diet-associated obesity</title>
      <link>/content/publication/poutahidis-microbial-2013-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/poutahidis-microbial-2013-1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbial symbionts accelerate wound healing via the neuropeptide hormone oxytocin</title>
      <link>/content/publication/poutahidis-microbial-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/content/publication/poutahidis-microbial-2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
